Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, Stanford Computer Forum Distinguished Lecture Series, Videorecordings V0058
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Videorecordings
  - Statistical Mechanics of Concurrency, by Prof. Yechiam Yemini., 1985-05-07; V0058.055; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 9)
    Consider a set of agents involved in a concurrent access to a shared distributed resource. Sharing is subject to interference constraints that define the set of admissible configurations of concurrent activities. Examples of such interference systems include transactions sharing a database, packet transmissions sharing the ether in a packet radio network and interprocessor communications sharing a switching network. The performance behavior of such systems has resisted traditional analysis techniques. I will present a statistical mechanics approach to the analysis of interference systems. This approach facilitates solutions of complex distributed systems, offers physical insights to their behavior and potentially useful tools in their design using physical performance measures (e.g., "pressure" of a data base), and provides access to a wide body of methods of physics to solve such systems.
  - Postscript, by Prof. Brian K. Reid. Edited Master., 1985-05-22; V0058.056; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 10)
    PostScript is an executable language for the description of graphical images. It was developed by a local company, Adobe Systems, and is implemented in several commercially-available laser printers and phototypesetters.
  - Transparency in Distributed Operating Systems, by Prof. Gerald 1. Popek. Edited master., 1985-06-05; V0058.057; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 10)
    invisible, to both people and programs. Access to all resources, bey they data, tasks, devices, services, etc. is the same, independent of the location of the requestor or the resource. This concept is akin to the manner by which virtual memory in operating systems hides the distinction between main and secondary storage, or the way data independence in database systems separates the means of information access from access paths, storage structures, etc. Denning argues that transparency is an important, fundamental design principle. Consider a distributed computing environment composed of thousands of computing nodes (workstations, mainframes, etc.), with perhaps different processor types, and even different operating systems in some cases. Is it feasible to provide a high level of transparency? Is it desirable? These issues will be raised, resulting architectural and design problems outlined, and the current state of their solutions in the Locus distributed operating system family discussed. Some of the problems include name service in a very large scale system, CPU and data type heterogeneity, and integration of foreign operating systems.
  - Belief. Awareness, and Limited Reasoning, by Dr. Joe Halpern. Edited master., 1985-10-01; V0058.058; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 10)
    Classical possible-worlds models for knowledge and belief suffer from the problem of logical omniscience: agents know all tautologies and their knowledge is closed under logical consequence. This unfortunately is not a very accurate account of how people operate! We review possible-worlds semantics, and then go on to introduce three approaches towards solving the problem of logical omniscience. In particular, in our logics, the set of beliefs of an agent does not necessarily contain all valid formulas. One of our logics deals explicitly with awareness, where, roughly speaking, it is necessary to be aware of a concept before one can have beliefs about it. Another gives a model of local reasoning, where an agent is viewed as a society of minds, each with its own cluster of beliefs, which may contradict each other. The talk with be completely self-contained.
  - Challenges and Directions in Fault-Tolerant Computing, by Dr. Jack Goldberg. Edited master., 1985-10-02; V0058.059; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 10)
    Two decades of theoretical and experimental work and numerous recent successful applications have established fault tolerance as a standard objective in computer system design. As with the objective of correctness, and in contrast to the objective of high speed, satisfaction of fault tolerance requirements cannot be demonstrated by testing alone, but requires formal analysis. Most of the work in fault tolerance has been concerned with developing effective design techniques. Recent work on reliability modeling and formal proof of fault tolerant design and implementation is laying a foundation for a more rigorous design discipline. The scope of concern has also expanded to include any source of computer reliability, such as design mistakes, in software, hardware, or at any system level. Current art is barely able to keep up with the rapid pace of computer technology, the stresses of new applications and the new expansion in scope of concerns. Particular challenges lie in coping with imperfections of the ultrasmall, i.e., high-density VLSI, and the ultra-large, i.e., large software systems. It is clear that fault tolerance cannot be "added" to a design and must be integrated with other design objectives. Simultaneous demands in future systems for high performance, high security, high evolvability and high fault tolerance will require new theoretical models of computer systems and a much closer integration of practical design techniques. The talk will discuss the widening scope of research into computer dependability. New issues include tolerance of design errors (including software), operator errors, and the safety of computer-controlled systems.
  - Common Loops--A Graceful Merger of Lisp and Object Oriented Programming, by Dr. Daniel G. Bobrow. Edited master., 1985-11-06; V0058.060; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 10)
    CommonLoops merges the facilities of object oriented programming and Lisp. This talk will briefly describe the relevant features of the two styles of programming, and describe the unique properties of this merge. These include a uniform syntax for function calling and sending messages; amerger of the type space of Lisp and the class hierarchy of objects; a generalization of method specification that includes ordinary Lisp functions at one extreme, and fully type specified functions at the other; and a "metaclass" mechanism that allows tradeoffs between early binding and ease of exploratory programming in the implementation of objects.
  - Perceptual Organization and the Representation of Natural Form, by Dr. Alex P. Pentland. Edited master., 1985-11-19; V0058.061; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 10)
    To understand both perception and commonsense reasoning we need a representation that captures important physical regularities and that correctly describes the people's perceptual organization of the stimulus. Unfortunately, the current representations were originally developed for other purposes (e.g., physics, engineering) and are therefore often unsuitable. We have developed a new representation and used it to make accurate descriptions of an extensive variety of natural forms including people, mountains, clouds and trees. The descriptions are amazingly compact. The approach of this representation is to describe scene structure in a manner similar to people's notion of "a part," suing descriptions that reflect a possible formative history of the object, e.g., how the object might have been constructed from lumps of clay. For this representation to be useful it must be possible to recover such descriptions from image data; we show that the primitive elements of such descriptions may be recovered in an overconstrained and therefore reliable manner. An interactive "real time" 3-D graphics modeling system based on this representation will be shown, together with short animated sequences demonstrating the descriptive power of the representation.
  - A Knowledge-Based Approach to High-Level Program Optimization, by Prof. Allen Goldberg., 1985-12-10; V0058.062; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 11)
    Our concern is the compilation of high-level declarative programs into efficient Pascallevel implementations. Specifications are written as equational assertions over a settheoretic data domain. Compilation is achieved by semi-automatic application of source-to-source transformations. These transformations formalize knowledge about high-level optimization techniques required for the task. These techniques include finite differencing, loop fusion, algebraic simplification, symbolic evaluation, data structure selection, and store-vs-compute. The relevance of this work to the optimization of Prolog and functional programs will be discussed.
  - The GF11 Supercomputer, by Dr. John F. Beetem. Edited master., 1986-01-21; V0058.063; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 11)
    GF11 is a parallel computer currently under construction at the IBM Yorktown Research Center. The machine incorporates 576 floating-point processors arranged in a modified SIMD architecture. Each processor has space for 3 Mbytes of memory and is capable of 20 Mflops, giving the total machine a peak of 1.125 Gbytes of memory and 11 .52 Gflops. The processors are interconnected by a dynamically reconfigurable non-blocking switching network. At each machine cycle, any of 1024 pre- selected permutations of data can be realized among the processors. The main intended application of GF11 is a class of calculations arising from quantum chromodynamics, a proposed theory of the elementary particles which participate in nuclear interactions.
  - Technology Trends of CMOS VLSI, Dr. Y oshio Nishi., 1986-01-22; V0058.064; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 11)
    As a mainstream technology for the VLSI!ULSI era, CMOS technology has attracted increasing attention and absorbs a tremendous amount of R&D resources. This seminar will cover the historical background of CMOS technology, recent progress in VLSI CMOS technology, and application of CMOS technology to the latest VLSI devices. Also discussed will be several topics in device physics and fabrication process technology for submicron CMOS.
  - Juno, A Constraint-Based Graphics System, by Dr. Greg Nelson. Edited master., 1986-02-04; V0058.065; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 11)
    Juno is a system that harmoniously integrates a language for describing computer graphics images with a what-you-see-is- what-you-get image editor. Two of Juno's novelties are that geometric constraints are used to specify locations, and that the text of a Juno program is modified in response to the interactive editing of the displayed image that the program produces. A videotape of the program will be shown; the research was done at Xerox P ARC.
  - Sprite OS, by Prof. John Ousterhout. Edited Master., 1986-02-12; V0058.066; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 11)
    Sprite is a new network operating system being built at Berkeley as part of the SPUR workstation project. The talk will focus on three parts of Sprite: the filesystem, process offloading, and the virtual memory system. The filesystem will provide a single shared Unix-like file hierarchy distributed across several servers. Clients will use dynamically-constructed prefix tables to associate file names with servers. Sprite will include a process offloading mechanism that allows jobs to be run on idle workstations in the same way that jobs may be placed in background in Unix. The virtual memory system will be Unix-like with simple extensions to permit shared data segments and synchronization.
  - Lattices and Algorithms, by Prof. Laszlo Lovasz. Edited master., 1986-02-18; V0058.067; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 11)
    Given a lattice L in the n-dimensional space, we may ask several questions like "Which is the shortest non-zero vector in L?", "Which point of L is closest to a given point in the space?", etc. Many classical results in the "Geometry of Numbers" deal with these questions from a non-algorithmic point of view. However, algorithmic aspects of them only recently became objects of extensive study, to a large extent because of their applications in algebra, cryptography, combinatorial optimization, prime number theory, etc. Moreover, renewed interest in this field has resulted in substantial improvements of classical results.
  - Man Dies due to Poor Man-Machine Interface Design, by Chuck Clanton. Edited Master., 1986-02-19; V0058.068; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 12)
    Few dispute that interactions between computers and users requires thoughtful attention. Is this a communication of craft or idiosyncrasies of personal taste? Placebo effects and fundamental principles are difficult to distinguish. This talk recounts some of the inadequately controlled and poorly validated experiments by the speaker which lend insights into the current state of the art.
  - Cache Memories, by Alan Smith. Master., 1986-04-02; V0058.069; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 12)
    Cache memories are used in almost all large and medium size computers in order to reduce the average main memory access time. Cache memories are also in use with, or being built for (or on), high performance microprocessors. In this talk, we provide an overview of the issues in cache memory design, concentrating on some recent work by the speaker. Particular attention is given to cache workloads, cache consistency mechanisms, and the miss ratio as a function of line size and cache size. Other topic may include: cache fetch algorithms (demand vs. prefetch), placement (set associative, direct mapping, etc.) and replacement (LRU, FIFO, etc.) algorithms, store through vs. copy back updating of main memory, cold start vs. warm start miss ratios, the effect of input/output through the cache, virtual address caches, user/supervisor caches, multilevel cache, the behavior of split instruction! data caches, and translation lookaside buffers
  - Complexity Theoretic Aspects of Linear Programming, by Steven Smale. Master., 1986-04-29; V0058.070; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 12)
    An exposition of some results on the speed of basic linear programming complementarity problems. Some relationship to Newton's method are also being developed
  - The H-P Precision Architecture, by Jerry Huck. Master., 1986-04-30; V0058.071; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 12)
    HP's Spectrum Program has defined and is implementing a completely new family of computer systems using a RISC based architecture. This talk focuses on the processor organization to examine CPU resources, instruction set, and storage organization. Started by a small research group at HP's central labs, the concepts of RISC computer design were applied to a new architecture suitable for both commercial and technical applications. The architecture adheres to the basic tenet: "Make the most frequent functions go as fast as possible." Compiler writers, operating systems experts, and hardware designers iterated through a proposal-paper design cycle to optimize an architecture for maximum throughput. The first member of the family has been announced and the presentation discusses the organization and implementation of its CPU.
  - Synthesizing Realistic Textures by the Composition of Perceptually Motivated Functions and Programming Language Design, by Ken Perlin. Master., 1986-05-06; V0058.072; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 12)
    This research demonstrates a uniform functional composition framework for modeling and synthesizing complex textures. The appearance of a wide range of natural phenomena can be expressed and efficiently synthesized in this framework. Animation of texture is readily incorporated. Emphasis will be on explaining the properties leading to generality, expressivity, and efficiency. A system is described in which an image is approximated by a finite collection of .B samples, representing neighborhoods in the image. The user designs visual simulations of surface textures by constructing an algorithm that is to be independently computed at each image sample. Primitive functions are provided to allow control within the texture algorithm of such visually important texture properties as frequency and first order spatial statistics. The user proceeds by building from these functions. Feedback is provided by images indicating the state of any computed quantity over all samples. The system includes primitive functions that facilitate the manipulation of such visually discriminable qualities as brightness, contrast, coherent discontinuities, orientation, and features possessing restricted ranges of frequency. These primitive functions are used to build up composite functions that facilitate the manipulation of more sophisticated visual qualities. The system is applied to build the appearance of such textures as water, star fields, flame, marble, clouds, stucco, rock, smoke, and soap films. Major results are twofold. First I will show that a wide range of naturalistic visual textures can be constructed with this approach. Second, I will demonstrate specific functions that encode visual elements common to disparate visual textures.
  - The NCUBE Family of Parallel Supercomputers, by John Palmer., 1986-05-14; V0058.073; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 12)
    NCUBE has developed a family of parallel computer systems based on a proprietary VLSI process that was designed specifi- cally for parallel computing. The NCUBE systems range from 8 MIPS (2 mflops) for a 4-node board to 2000 MIPS (500 rnfIops) in a 1,024 processor system. There are three versions of the NCUBE system: NCUBE/4: a 4-node board that plugs into an IBM PC-AT; NCUBEI7: an office environment system up to 128 nodes; NCUBEIlO: a true supercomputer with up to 1,024 nodes. In addition to high computational performance, the NCUBE family has a unique high performance I/O system. the I/O system is expandable from 1-8 channels each of which is capable of 180 mbytes/sec transfer rate. This allows for very high performance graphics support and parallel disk interfaces. The NCUBE family along with its software support is covered in the presentation. Also a COMPAQ with an NCUBE/4 is used in demonstration
  - Nanocomputers and Molecular Engineering, by K. Eric Drexler., 1986-10-21; V0058.074; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 13)
    The broad outlines of future technology will be set by the limits of physical law, if we can develop means for approaching those limits. Today, because we cannot directly manipulate the atomic building blocks of matter, we can make no more than a tiny fraction of the physical structures permitted by natural law. But advances in biotechnology and computational chemistry are opening a path to the development of molecular assemblers able to build objects to complex atomic specifications, removing this constraint and making possible dramatic advances in many fields. Among these advances will be nanocomputers with parts of molecular size. Mechanical nanocomputers--molecular Babbage machines--are amenable to design and analysis with available techniques: this technology promises sub-micron computers with gigahertz clock rates, nanowatt power dissipation, and RAM storage densities in the hundreds of millions of terabits per cubic centimeter
  - Architectural Innovations in the AT&T CRISP Microprocessor, by David Ditzel., 1987-03-04; V0058.075; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 13)
    The AT&T CRISP Microprocessor is a high performance C Machine. CRISP is a general purpose single chip 32-bit processor containing 172,163 transistors. The instructions-set architecture is that of a registerless 2 112 address memory-to-memory machine with a small number of instructions and addressing modes. The CRISP instruction-set is relatively independent of any particular implementation. High performance is achieved by pipelining, caches, an efficient instruction-set, and several new architectural techniques. A 128-byte on-chip stack cache provides automatic register allocation in hardware. Branch folding allows branch instructions to execute in zero time. This talk describes some of the more innovative aspects of CRISP's hardware architecture
  - Updating Deductive Databases in Logic, by David Scott Warren., 1987-03-10; V0058.076; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 13)
    Prolog adds a notion of procedurality to Horn clause logic by using a particular proof procedure, SLD resolution. Global state changes are effected in Prolog as side-effects of this proof procedure, and as a result can only be understood in a very syntactic way. We have developed a theory, based on modal logic, that adds procedurality to Horn clause logic in a more semantic way. This theory is applied to the problem of updating deductive databases, and results in a declarative semantics for database transactions. We show connections to a logical notion of null values and database triggers. We show how some transactions that update database views can be understood as statements in a particularly simple and elegant dynamic logic. We describe the current state of an implementation of a prototype concurrent, distributed, deductive database with an update language based on this logic.
  - Software Standards and Hardware Advances: The Driving Forces for Open Systems, by Andy Bechtolsheim., 1987-03-11; V0058.077; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 13)
    This talk discusses the advances in workstation technology which have occurred over the last five years and which have enabled us to build open systems interconnecting a wide range of computer equipment. We will cover the role of operating systems, networking, windowsystems, and graphics technology in the evolution of standards. Speculations will be made on possible developments in the next five years.
  - Servant: A New Shell for the MAC, by Andy Hertzfeld., 1987-04-01; V0058.078; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 13)
    Servant is a new MAC shell replacing the FINDER, the most common shell for the MAC. The goal in designing Servant is to help evolve the MAC user interface into the late eighties. The program has four major elements: a second generation browser, intuitive multitasking support for rapid switching between applications, customizes to allow better allocation of resources, and user programmability at the shell level. This talk will demonstrate the program and discuss the design constraints and tradeoffs for Servant in the MAC environment.
  - An Introduction to the Probabilistic Analysis of Combinatorial Algorithms, by Richard Karp., 1987-05-19; V0058.079; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 13)
    In fields such as operations research, artificial intelligence and computer-aided design, algorithms are often used that perform well in practice even though there is no theoretical guarantee of their good performance. The simplex algorithm for linear programming is perhaps he most notable example of this phenomenon. It is a major challenge to algorithm designers to provide foundation for such quick-anddirty heuristic algorithms. One approach is through probabilistic analysis, in which one defines a probability distribution over the set of instances of a problem, and then endeavors to prove that some fast, simple algorithm performs well with a high probability. The speaker will discuss this approach, using examples related to set partitioning, bin packing and linear programming. He will then make an assessment of the strengths and weaknesses of probabilistic analysis as a method of validating quick-and-dirty algorithms
  - Why Computers Stop, by Jim Gray., 1988-10-07; V0058.080; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 14)
    Conventional computers stop because of hardware, software, environment, and people. Fault-tolerant computers stop for the conventional reasons, but the statistics are different. This talk discusses the statistics and approaches to fault tolerance.